<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>HCI² Research Lab</title><link>https://hci2.uk/</link><atom:link href="https://hci2.uk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>HCI² Research Lab</description><generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://hci2.uk/media/logo_hu15880263399225826474.png</url><title>HCI² Research Lab</title><link>https://hci2.uk/</link></image><item><title>teaching</title><link>https://hci2.uk/teaching/ai/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hci2.uk/teaching/ai/</guid><description/></item><item><title>teaching</title><link>https://hci2.uk/teaching/icps/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hci2.uk/teaching/icps/</guid><description>&lt;!-- ---
title: teaching
date: 2025-11-23
type: landing
sections:
- block: features
content:
title: Industrial Cyber-Physical Systems
text: ''
items:
- name: "Industrial Cyber-Physical Systems"
description: |
**Principal lecturer:** Dr Bugra Alkan &lt;br>
**Taken by:** Level 7 MSc Applied Artificial Intelligence and related programmes &lt;br>
**Term:** Semester 2 &lt;br>
**Hours:** 33 (11 × 2h lectures + 11 × 1h tutorials) &lt;br>
**Format:** In-person lectures and labs &lt;br>
**Suggested hours of supervisions:** 4 &lt;br>
Module materials are available on its Moodle page.
---
### Aims
This module introduces Industrial Cyber-Physical Systems (ICPS) and Industrial Internet-of-Things (IIoT) analytics, with a focus on time-series data from industrial systems. It covers architectures for ICPS and smart factories, industrial networking and communication (including OPC-UA), IIoT data pipelines, time-series pre-processing, classical forecasting, feature-based machine learning, deep sequential models and anomaly detection.
The emphasis is on practical data analytics in Python for industrial time-series, including case studies drawn from robotics and smart manufacturing.
---
### Lectures
#### L1 Introduction to ICPS and IIoT Analytics
Motivation and module overview; from traditional automation to Industry 4.0; Industrial Cyber-Physical Systems (ICPS) at a glance; data, information and value in smart factories; informal ICPS and IIoT architectures; module structure and learning outcomes; Colab environment check and a first industrial time series; summary and exercises.
#### L2 Cyber-Physical Systems and Smart Factories
Definitions and characteristics of cyber-physical systems; smart factories and cyber-physical production systems; architectural views of ICPS; data flows in CPS and typical time-series characteristics (sampling, delays, noise, multivariate tags); safety, reliability and security considerations in industrial settings; summary and exercises.
#### L3 Internet-of-Things Connectivity and Networking
Networking basics relevant to ICPS (latency, bandwidth, reliability); Quality of Service (QoS) in industrial IoT; wired and wireless connectivity technologies (fieldbuses, Ethernet-based solutions, Wi-Fi, LPWAN, 5G, etc.); edge, fog and cloud in industrial networking; positioning computation along the edge–cloud continuum; M2M communication protocols (MQTT, CoAP, AMQP and others) and their suitability for industrial use; summary and exercises.
#### L4 Industrial Communication and OPC-UA
Overview of the industrial communication landscape; from OPC Classic to OPC-UA; OPC Unified Architecture concepts and design goals; OPC-UA address space and information modelling; services, subscriptions and data access; brief overview of OPC-UA security model; OPC-UA as a data backbone for IIoT analytics; summary and exercises.
#### L5 Introduction to IIoT Processing and Analytics
Motivation for analytics in IIoT and ICPS; types of data in IIoT (tags, events, logs); typical analytics tasks (monitoring, forecasting, predictive maintenance, optimisation); IIoT analytics pipelines from data acquisition to dashboards and decision support; IIoT data architectures and storage choices (historians, time-series databases, data lakes); time-series viewpoint on industrial tags; summary and exercises.
#### L6 Time Series Pre-processing for IIoT
Characteristics of IIoT time series (irregular sampling, bursts, drifts, multiple resolutions); aligning and resampling signals; handling missing data; outlier detection and treatment; smoothing and simple denoising; scaling and normalisation; constructing model-ready windows from raw tag streams; train/validation/test splits along time; summary and exercises.
#### L7 Classical Time Series Forecasting Methods
Forecasting problems in IIoT (loads, temperatures, vibration, quality metrics); decomposition into trend, seasonality and remainder; exponential smoothing methods; AR, MA, ARMA and ARIMA models; Seasonal ARIMA (SARIMA); comparison of classical approaches with ML/deep-learning-based forecasting (preview); summary and exercises.
#### L8 Feature-based Machine Learning for IIoT Forecasting
From time series to supervised learning formulation; feature engineering for IIoT forecasting (lags, rolling statistics, calendar and context features); linear models with regularisation (Ridge, Lasso); tree-based models for forecasting (random forests, gradient-boosted trees); evaluation and comparison with classical time-series baselines; Colab workflow for ML-based IIoT forecasting; summary and exercises.
#### L9 Deep Sequential Models for IIoT Forecasting
Sequence modelling setup for industrial time series; recurrent neural networks (RNNs); Long Short-Term Memory (LSTM) networks; Gated Recurrent Units (GRUs); Temporal Convolutional Networks (TCNs) and 1D CNNs for time series; training and regularisation for sequence models; brief note on multi-step forecasting strategies; summary and exercises.
#### L10 Anomaly Detection in ICPS and IIoT Time Series
What counts as an anomaly in industrial time series (point, contextual, collective anomalies); forecasting-residual-based anomaly detection; Isolation Forest for unsupervised anomaly detection; autoencoder-based anomaly detection; thresholding strategies, evaluation and practical considerations for operations; Colab workflow for anomaly detection; summary and exercises.
#### L11 Project Presentations: ICPS and IIoT Analytics in Practice
Student presentations of mini-projects using Python/Colab on ICPS/IIoT datasets and/or robotic systems; demonstration of complete pipelines from raw time-series data through pre-processing, forecasting and/or anomaly detection to visualisation and interpretation; peer feedback and reflective discussion on modelling choices, limitations and deployment considerations.
---
### Objectives
At the end of the course students should:
- Understand the role of ICPS, smart factories and IIoT in modern industrial systems.
- Be able to describe and compare ICPS/IIoT architectures, networking options and M2M protocols.
- Understand the purpose of OPC-UA and its role in industrial communication and analytics.
- Be able to design and implement IIoT analytics pipelines for time-series data in Python.
- Understand and apply key pre-processing techniques for industrial time series (alignment, cleaning, resampling, windowing, scaling).
- Be familiar with classical time-series forecasting methods (exponential smoothing, ARIMA, SARIMA) and know when to use them.
- Be able to engineer features and train machine-learning models (linear and tree-based) for IIoT forecasting and evaluate them properly.
- Understand the principles behind deep sequential models (RNNs, LSTMs, GRUs, TCNs) and apply them to industrial forecasting problems.
- Be able to implement and compare different approaches to anomaly detection in ICPS/IIoT data.
- Appreciate practical safety, reliability and security considerations in deploying analytics in industrial and robotic systems.
---
### Recommended reading
- Lee, E. A. *Introduction to Embedded Systems: A Cyber-Physical Systems Approach* (for CPS foundations).
- Hermann, M., Pentek, T. &amp; Otto, B. “Design principles for Industrie 4.0 scenarios” (Industry 4.0 / smart factories).
- Hyndman, R. J. &amp; Athanasopoulos, G. *Forecasting: Principles and Practice* (free online; classical forecasting).
- Bagnall, A. et al. selected papers/tutorials on time-series classification and forecasting.
- Chollet, F. *Deep Learning with Python* (selected chapters on sequence models).
design:
columns: "1"
--- --></description></item><item><title>HCI² Lab Presents- The 2025 Kilobot Swarm Intelligence Extra-Curricular Activity</title><link>https://hci2.uk/event/swarmexc/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hci2.uk/event/swarmexc/</guid><description>&lt;p>Slides can be added in a few ways:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Create&lt;/strong> slides using Wowchemy&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://docs.hugoblox.com/managing-content/#create-slides" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;em>Slides&lt;/em>&lt;/a> feature and link using &lt;code>slides&lt;/code> parameter in the front matter of the talk file&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Upload&lt;/strong> an existing slide deck to &lt;code>static/&lt;/code> and link using &lt;code>url_slides&lt;/code> parameter in the front matter of the talk file&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Embed&lt;/strong> your slides (e.g. Google Slides) or presentation video on this page using &lt;a href="https://docs.hugoblox.com/writing-markdown-latex/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">shortcodes&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Further event details, including page elements such as image galleries, can be added to the body of this page.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Spatial Augmented Reality in Manual Assembly: An Empirical Investigation of Its Effects on Assembly Performance and Cognitive Ergonomics</title><link>https://hci2.uk/publication/preprint/preprint2/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hci2.uk/publication/preprint/preprint2/</guid><description>&lt;!--
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Create your slides in Markdown - click the &lt;em>Slides&lt;/em> button to check out the example.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
Add the publication's **full text** or **supplementary notes** here. You can use rich formatting such as including [code, math, and images](https://docs.hugoblox.com/content/writing-markdown-latex/). --></description></item><item><title>A Novel Adaptive AMR Fleet Management System Leveraging AI-enabled Digital Twin for Agile Incident Response and Improved Shop-floor Efficiency</title><link>https://hci2.uk/publication/preprint/preprint1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hci2.uk/publication/preprint/preprint1/</guid><description>&lt;!--
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Create your slides in Markdown - click the &lt;em>Slides&lt;/em> button to check out the example.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
Add the publication's **full text** or **supplementary notes** here. You can use rich formatting such as including [code, math, and images](https://docs.hugoblox.com/content/writing-markdown-latex/). --></description></item><item><title>Gest-SAR: A Gesture-Controlled Spatial AR System for Interactive Manual Assembly Guidance with Real-Time Operational Feedback</title><link>https://hci2.uk/publication/journal-article/journal1/</link><pubDate>Sun, 27 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hci2.uk/publication/journal-article/journal1/</guid><description>&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Click the &lt;em>Cite&lt;/em> button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Create your slides in Markdown - click the &lt;em>Slides&lt;/em> button to check out the example.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Add the publication&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong>full text&lt;/strong> or &lt;strong>supplementary notes&lt;/strong> here. You can use rich formatting such as including &lt;a href="https://docs.hugoblox.com/content/writing-markdown-latex/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">code, math, and images&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A Comparative Study of Attention-Augmented YOLO Architectures for Defect Detection in Fused Deposition Modelling</title><link>https://hci2.uk/publication/conference-paper/conference2/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hci2.uk/publication/conference-paper/conference2/</guid><description>&lt;!--
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Click the &lt;em>Cite&lt;/em> button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Create your slides in Markdown - click the &lt;em>Slides&lt;/em> button to check out the example.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
Add the publication's **full text** or **supplementary notes** here. You can use rich formatting such as including [code, math, and images](https://docs.hugoblox.com/content/writing-markdown-latex/). --></description></item><item><title>Dynamic Trust Management for Secure Federated Learning in Critical Industrial and IoT Networks</title><link>https://hci2.uk/publication/conference-paper/conference1/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hci2.uk/publication/conference-paper/conference1/</guid><description>&lt;!--
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Click the &lt;em>Cite&lt;/em> button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Create your slides in Markdown - click the &lt;em>Slides&lt;/em> button to check out the example.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
Add the publication's **full text** or **supplementary notes** here. You can use rich formatting such as including [code, math, and images](https://docs.hugoblox.com/content/writing-markdown-latex/). --></description></item><item><title>State of the art and future directions of digital twin-enabled smart assembly automation in discrete manufacturing industries</title><link>https://hci2.uk/publication/journal-article/journal2/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hci2.uk/publication/journal-article/journal2/</guid><description>&lt;!--
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Click the &lt;em>Cite&lt;/em> button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Create your slides in Markdown - click the &lt;em>Slides&lt;/em> button to check out the example.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
Add the publication's **full text** or **supplementary notes** here. You can use rich formatting such as including [code, math, and images](https://docs.hugoblox.com/content/writing-markdown-latex/). --></description></item><item><title>People</title><link>https://hci2.uk/people/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hci2.uk/people/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Digital Twin-Enabled Adaptive Fleet Management</title><link>https://hci2.uk/research/digitaltwin/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hci2.uk/research/digitaltwin/</guid><description>&lt;div>
&lt;div>
&lt;p>&lt;b>Abstract:&lt;/b> This research presents a Digital Twin (DT)-enabled adaptive fleet management framework for Autonomous Mobile Robots (AMRs) in discrete manufacturing. The proposed multi-fidelity DT framework integrates high-fidelity simulation and surrogate optimisation models to enable real-time, incident-aware decision-making. It also introduces operator-in-the-loop interaction to support Industry 5.0’s human-centric principles, enhancing adaptability and resilience on the shop floor. &lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="container">
&lt;div class="column">This project develops an operator-centred Digital Twin framework for resilient Autonomous Mobile Robot (AMR) fleet management in dynamic smart manufacturing environments. Building on a multi-fidelity digital architecture that combines Digital Models, Digital Shadows, surrogate-based multi objective optimisation and high-fidelity simulation, the system detects incidents such as AMR failures, machine breakdowns and demand shocks, then generates incident aware schedules in real time. A lightweight surrogate model provides rapid rescheduling within a few seconds while remaining close to high fidelity reference behaviour, enabling throughput and energy efficiency to be preserved under disruption. In parallel, a human in the loop decision layer exposes Pareto fronts, Gantt chart previews and post simulation metrics to operators, who can select preferred trade-offs, request validation via re simulation or issue policy bound overrides, all under role-based access control. Every decision is captured as a machine-readable artefact with timestamps, reason codes and override rationale, creating a single audited trail that supports governance, cross shift handover and future learning from operator choices. The framework will be instantiated and evaluated on a battery module assembly line, providing benchmark evidence on latency, robustness and operator workload for different policy modes prioritising speed, assurance or governance, and delivering a transferable blueprint for Industry 5.0 ready, human centric AMR coordination.
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="column">&lt;img>&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;!-- This project develops an operator-centred Digital Twin framework for resilient Autonomous Mobile Robot (AMR) fleet management in dynamic smart manufacturing environments. Building on a multi-fidelity digital architecture that combines Digital Models, Digital Shadows, surrogate-based multi objective optimisation and high-fidelity simulation, the system detects incidents such as AMR failures, machine breakdowns and demand shocks, then generates incident aware schedules in real time. A lightweight surrogate model provides rapid rescheduling within a few seconds while remaining close to high fidelity reference behaviour, enabling throughput and energy efficiency to be preserved under disruption. In parallel, a human in the loop decision layer exposes Pareto fronts, Gantt chart previews and post simulation metrics to operators, who can select preferred trade-offs, request validation via re simulation or issue policy bound overrides, all under role-based access control. Every decision is captured as a machine-readable artefact with timestamps, reason codes and override rationale, creating a single audited trail that supports governance, cross shift handover and future learning from operator choices. The framework will be instantiated and evaluated on a battery module assembly line, providing benchmark evidence on latency, robustness and operator workload for different policy modes prioritising speed, assurance or governance, and delivering a transferable blueprint for Industry 5.0 ready, human centric AMR coordination. -->
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="project-publications">
&lt;h3>Related Publications&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://hci2.uk/publication/preprint/preprint1/">A Novel Adaptive AMR Fleet Management System Leveraging AI-enabled Digital Twin for Agile Incident Response and Improved Shop-floor Efficiency&lt;/a> — Louie, Osman M. Tokhi, Bugra&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://hci2.uk/publication/journal-article/journal2/">State of the art and future directions of digital twin-enabled smart assembly automation in discrete manufacturing industries&lt;/a> — Louie, Osman M. Tokhi, Bugra&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Vision-Enabled SAR for Manual Assembly</title><link>https://hci2.uk/research/sar/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hci2.uk/research/sar/</guid><description>
&lt;div class="project-publications">
&lt;h3>Related Publications&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://hci2.uk/publication/preprint/preprint2/">Spatial Augmented Reality in Manual Assembly: An Empirical Investigation of Its Effects on Assembly Performance and Cognitive Ergonomics&lt;/a> — Bugra, Naimul, Louie, Malarvizhi Kaniappan Chinnathai&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://hci2.uk/publication/journal-article/journal1/">Gest-SAR: A Gesture-Controlled Spatial AR System for Interactive Manual Assembly Guidance with Real-Time Operational Feedback&lt;/a> — Naimul, Bugra&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/div></description></item></channel></rss>