<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Ongoing Research Projects | HCI² Research Lab</title><link>https://hci2.uk/research/</link><atom:link href="https://hci2.uk/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Ongoing Research Projects</description><generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><image><url>https://hci2.uk/media/logo_hu15880263399225826474.png</url><title>Ongoing Research Projects</title><link>https://hci2.uk/research/</link></image><item><title>Human-in-the-Loop Digital Twin for Resilient AMR Fleet Management</title><link>https://hci2.uk/research/digitaltwin/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hci2.uk/research/digitaltwin/</guid><description>&lt;p>This project develops a multi-fidelity, policy-oriented Digital Twin (DT) for resilient Autonomous Mobile Robot (AMR) fleet management under disruption. The system monitors shop-floor telemetry via OPC-UA, classifies incidents (e.g., AMR breakdown, machine unavailability, demand shock), snapshots decision-relevant state, then generates incident-aware recovery schedules under a strict decision-time cap. A surrogate (low-fidelity) optimisation layer produces deployable responses within seconds, while a high-fidelity DT simulation layer provides audit, assurance, and post-decision validation. An operator-in-the-loop panel exposes Pareto trade-offs and schedule previews, enabling transparent selection, re-simulation on demand, and policy-bound overrides, with provenance captured as machine-readable decision artefacts.&lt;/p>
&lt;details class="expand-card">
&lt;summary class="expand-card-title">Motivation&lt;/summary>
&lt;div class="expand-card-body">As AMR fleets scale, small disruptions propagate into congestion, energy waste, and missed throughput targets. Rule-based fleet managers are fast but brittle and opaque during incidents, while high-fidelity simulation is informative but too slow for time-critical response. This project addresses the gap with a governed multi-fidelity DT, fast enough for real-time recovery, and structured enough for auditability, human oversight, and Industry 5.0–ready deployment.&lt;/div>
&lt;/details>
&lt;div class="project-digitaltwin">
&lt;details class="expand-card">
&lt;summary class="expand-card-title">System Architecture&lt;/summary>
&lt;div class="expand-card-body">&lt;h3 id="physical--communication-layer">&lt;strong>Physical &amp;amp; Communication Layer&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>AMRs, stations, sensors, and execution systems stream telemetry and events via &lt;strong>OPC-UA&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Event-driven incident triggers (e.g., fault flags, demand-change flags) initiate response&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="data--digital-shadow-layer">&lt;strong>Data &amp;amp; Digital Shadow Layer&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Telemetry is contextualised and stored (time-series + event envelopes)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>On incident, the system snapshots decision-relevant state, remaining jobs, resource availability, and constraints&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="digital-layer-multi-fidelity-decision-support">&lt;strong>Digital Layer, Multi-Fidelity Decision Support&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Surrogate optimisation (low-fidelity)&lt;/strong>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Generates recovery schedules under a strict decision-time budget&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Targets throughput (makespan) and energy-related objectives&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>High-fidelity DT simulation&lt;/strong>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Executes candidate schedules to validate behavioural realism (e.g., interactions, congestion effects)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Used for audit, assurance, and scenario analysis&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="humanmachine-interaction-layer-operator-panel">&lt;strong>Human–Machine Interaction Layer (Operator Panel)&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Live incident status and fleet state&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Pareto front exploration (trade-off selection)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Gantt schedule previews and validation&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Re-simulation requests and policy-bound overrides with rationale&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="governance--provenance-layer">&lt;strong>Governance &amp;amp; Provenance Layer&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Every incident and decision step is logged with timestamps, reason codes, response type, and operator actions&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Artefacts support traceability, cross-shift handover, and post hoc analysis&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/details>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="project-digitaltwin">
&lt;details class="expand-card">
&lt;summary class="expand-card-title">Key Components&lt;/summary>
&lt;div class="expand-card-body">&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Incident Response Module (IRM)&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Detects incidents from OPC-UA alerts, classifies event type, snapshots state, and triggers recovery.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Response Selector &amp;amp; Model Allocation&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Chooses surrogate-only response vs surrogate + audit vs high-fidelity escalation depending on incident severity, policy, and confidence.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Surrogate-Based Optimisation&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Multi-objective rescheduling under time constraints, balancing throughput and energy-related KPIs while enforcing feasibility and safety constraints.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>High-Fidelity DT Audit&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Validates surrogate decisions, quantifies surrogate–simulation agreement, and provides assurance evidence under disruption.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Operator Panel (Human-in-the-Loop)&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Supports trade-off selection (Pareto), schedule inspection (Gantt), re-simulation, and controlled overrides.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Decision Artefacts &amp;amp; Incident Log&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Structured outputs (status JSON, Pareto results, schedule images, metrics, incident log) enabling governance and reproducibility.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/details>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="project-digitaltwin">
&lt;details class="expand-card">
&lt;summary class="expand-card-title">Evaluation&lt;/summary>
&lt;div class="expand-card-body">&lt;p>The framework is instantiated in an intralogistics use case representing a &lt;strong>battery module assembly flowshop&lt;/strong>, where AMRs transport materials between stations. Evaluation introduces controlled disruption classes to stress-test response performance:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>AMR Breakdown (AMRBD)&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Transport capacity loss, task reassignment, utilisation shift.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Machine Breakdown (MBD)&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Reduced station availability, increased queueing pressure, precedence constraints.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Demand Change (DC)&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
High-priority job injection, schedule reordering, system-wide stress.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Metrics and evidence&lt;/strong> focus on:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Decision latency (stage-resolved, including detection, optimisation, audit/re-simulation, dispatch)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Makespan and energy deviation relative to nominal and baseline dispatch rules&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Schedule stability (reassignments and disturbance propagation)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Surrogate–simulation agreement (validity under high-fidelity execution)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Governance behaviour (policy modes, fidelity escalation, operator intervention pathways)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/details>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="project-digitaltwin">
&lt;details class="expand-card">
&lt;summary class="expand-card-title">Key Findings&lt;/summary>
&lt;div class="expand-card-body">&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Seconds-level incident recovery&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Surrogate optimisation delivers time-bounded rescheduling appropriate for operational incident response.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Multi-fidelity assurance&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
High-fidelity DT execution provides an auditable validation layer, enabling confidence-aware escalation rather than blanket simulation.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Human-in-the-loop governance&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Operator panel interactions (trade-off selection, validation requests, overrides) support accountable decision-making without sacrificing responsiveness.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Transferable blueprint&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
A policy-oriented architecture for AMR fleet management that generalises to other disruption-prone discrete manufacturing intralogistics settings.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/details>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Human-State Aware Human-Robot Collaborative Disassembly via Adaptive Agent Models, Negotiation, and Predictive Digital Twins</title><link>https://hci2.uk/research/hrc/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hci2.uk/research/hrc/</guid><description>&lt;p>This project develops a &lt;strong>human-state aware Human-Robot Collaboration (HRC) framework&lt;/strong> tailored for &lt;strong>end-of-life (EoL) disassembly&lt;/strong> of high-value products, where uncertainty, variability, and safety constraints make static task allocation brittle. The central contribution is an integrated architecture in which &lt;strong>human and robot agent models&lt;/strong> are continuously updated from operational data, including &lt;strong>operator physiological and cognitive state proxies&lt;/strong> (for example fatigue, stress, workload), enabling collaboration policies that respond to human condition and task context rather than assuming a fixed-capacity operator.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A key design choice is &lt;strong>negotiated, runtime task allocation&lt;/strong>, not purely centralised optimisation. The human agent can express preferences and constraints in-the-loop, and the system converges to an executable plan through negotiation and conflict resolution. A &lt;strong>predictive digital twin&lt;/strong> provides a validation layer, simulating task-level and agent-level dynamics to anticipate KPI impacts, task duration drift, and fatigue accumulation before committing to allocations.&lt;/p>
&lt;details class="expand-card">
&lt;summary class="expand-card-title">Motivation&lt;/summary>
&lt;div class="expand-card-body">Disassembly remains labour-intensive because it is nonlinear, context-dependent, and highly variable. Robots can deliver precision and repeatability, but effective collaboration fails when assistance is insensitive to operator condition and rapidly changing shop-floor realities. Conventional HRC approaches in disassembly often rely on static allocations and do not integrate real-time ergonomics, workload, and trust calibration into the collaboration loop. This project targets adaptive and human-centric HRC where allocation and assistance policies react to operator state to reduce risk, prevent overload, and improve long-term wellbeing while maintaining throughput.&lt;/div>
&lt;/details>
&lt;div class="project-industrialai">
&lt;details class="expand-card">
&lt;summary class="expand-card-title">System Architecture&lt;/summary>
&lt;div class="expand-card-body">&lt;h3 id="adaptive-agent-modelling-human-and-robot">&lt;strong>Adaptive Agent Modelling (Human and Robot)&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Capability profiles, tool availability, and skill descriptors&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Behavioural descriptors, e.g., preferences, workload thresholds, collaboration acceptance&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Real-time human-state proxies, e.g., fatigue trends, stress indicators, workload and engagement cues&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="task-decomposition-engine-disassembly-aware">&lt;strong>Task Decomposition Engine (Disassembly-Aware)&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Converts disassembly objectives into executable task graphs&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Encodes precedence and dependency logic essential for safe sequencing&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Supports product structure signals (BoM/CAD where available) plus contextual constraints&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="negotiation-based-collaboration-and-allocation">&lt;strong>Negotiation-Based Collaboration and Allocation&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Multi-objective allocation across efficiency, feasibility, and ergonomics&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Negotiation layer enabling runtime preference updates and constraints&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Conflict resolution to ensure convergence to an agreed, executable plan&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="predictive-digital-twin-validation-layer">&lt;strong>Predictive Digital Twin Validation Layer&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Simulates system-level and agent-level state evolution over candidate plans&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Forecasts KPIs, e.g., cycle time, workload accumulation, recovery likelihood, stability under uncertainty&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Feeds predictions back into allocation and negotiation to improve robustness&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="interface-and-human-in-the-loop-control">&lt;strong>Interface and Human-in-the-Loop Control&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Visualises operator load, task status, and key safety indicators&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Supports escalation and override pathways for practical deployment&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/details>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="project-industrialai">
&lt;details class="expand-card">
&lt;summary class="expand-card-title">Key Components&lt;/summary>
&lt;div class="expand-card-body">&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Human State Model&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
A digital representation of operator condition that updates continuously and is used to prevent unsafe allocations and reduce ergonomic strain.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Disassembly Task Graph Builder&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Generates precedence-constrained task graphs so allocation decisions are executable, context-correct, and aligned with disassembly constraints.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Negotiation-Enhanced Task Allocation&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Allows the human agent to accept, reject, or modify allocations based on fairness, effort, ergonomics, and situational feasibility, improving autonomy and collaboration quality.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Predictive Digital Twin Forecaster&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Anticipates timing drift and workload accumulation, enabling proactive planning rather than reactive recovery.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Risk-Aware Execution Hooks&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Safety-aware triggers for slow-down, pause, re-plan, or request confirmation when uncertainty or risk increases.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/details>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="project-industrialai">
&lt;details class="expand-card">
&lt;summary class="expand-card-title">Evaluation&lt;/summary>
&lt;div class="expand-card-body">&lt;p>The framework is designed for validation in an HRC testbed with repeatable EoL disassembly scenarios and controlled variability.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Evaluation focus includes:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Robustness of allocation under changing human state and contextual shifts&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ergonomic outcomes (proxy measures) and reduced overload or fatigue accumulation&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Task performance KPIs (cycle time, recovery frequency, stability under uncertainty)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Collaboration quality, including allocation acceptance and perceived usability&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Traceability of decisions, e.g., why an allocation changed and what state signals triggered it&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/details>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="project-industrialai">
&lt;details class="expand-card">
&lt;summary class="expand-card-title">Expected Outcomes&lt;/summary>
&lt;div class="expand-card-body">&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Safer collaboration under variability&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Adaptive policies reduce risk when operator condition deteriorates or the context becomes uncertain.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Better workload balancing&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Allocation decisions explicitly consider operator state, not just nominal task times or static capability assumptions.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Disassembly-ready HRC planning&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Task graphs and constraints reflect real disassembly dependencies, enabling executable and safer collaboration plans.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Deployable governance posture&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Negotiation traces and digital twin forecasts support post hoc analysis, justification, and continuous improvement.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/details>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Safety-Aware Anomaly Detection and RUL Analytics for Industrial Machinery</title><link>https://hci2.uk/research/anomaly/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hci2.uk/research/anomaly/</guid><description>&lt;p>This project develops a safety-aware anomaly detection and RUL analytics pipeline for industrial machinery, grounded in demonstrator evidence rather than purely offline datasets. Using the bottle inspection and sorting system, we capture multi-sensor telemetry (signals from actuators, conveyors, inspection modules, and control logic), align it into machine-state segments, then learn normal operational signatures to detect deviation patterns early. Beyond detection, the framework estimates degradation trends and Remaining Useful Life with uncertainty bounds, enabling maintenance planning that is both operationally useful and defensible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A core requirement is auditability, every alert is paired with traceable evidence (when the deviation started, which signals contributed, confidence/uncertainty, and operator validation outcome), enabling post hoc analysis, governance, and cross-shift handover.&lt;/p>
&lt;details class="expand-card">
&lt;summary class="expand-card-title">Motivation&lt;/summary>
&lt;div class="expand-card-body">Industrial anomaly detection is often evaluated on static datasets, but deployment fails when alarms are noisy, poorly explained, or misaligned with safety and operational decision-making. In inspection and sorting cells, late fault detection can create cascading issues, mis-sorts, quality escapes, downtime spikes, and unsafe recovery actions. This project focuses on &lt;strong>early and explainable detection&lt;/strong>, &lt;strong>RUL-style forecasting&lt;/strong>, and &lt;strong>human verification&lt;/strong>, so the outputs are usable in real maintenance and operations workflows.&lt;/div>
&lt;/details>
&lt;div class="project-industrialai">
&lt;details class="expand-card">
&lt;summary class="expand-card-title">System Architecture&lt;/summary>
&lt;div class="expand-card-body">&lt;h3 id="sensing--control-layer">&lt;strong>Sensing &amp;amp; Control Layer&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Demonstrator telemetry from PLC/control events plus sensor streams (time-series + event logs)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Production context signals, e.g., mode, recipe, throughput rate, inspection outcomes&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="data-layer">&lt;strong>Data Layer&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Synchronisation, cleaning, and machine-cycle segmentation&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Feature store for time-domain, frequency-domain, and event-derived features&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ground-truth support via fault logs, interventions, and controlled fault injection (where feasible)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="learning-layer-detection--prognostics">&lt;strong>Learning Layer (Detection + Prognostics)&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Anomaly Detection&lt;/strong>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Learns normal operational signatures per mode/recipe&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Detects deviations using confidence-aware thresholds and persistence logic&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>RUL / Degradation Modelling&lt;/strong>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Health indicator construction and trend modelling&lt;/li>
&lt;li>RUL prediction with uncertainty bounds (intervals), not just point estimates&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="human-in-the-loop-layer">&lt;strong>Human-in-the-Loop Layer&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Alarm triage panel, operator labels, “confirmed / not an issue / needs monitoring”&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Feedback improves calibration, reduces false positives, and builds trust&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="governance--audit-layer">&lt;strong>Governance &amp;amp; Audit Layer&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Alarm evidence packs, timestamps, signal attribution, and decision rationale&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Machine-readable artefacts enabling traceability and reproducibility&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/details>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="project-industrialai">
&lt;details class="expand-card">
&lt;summary class="expand-card-title">Key Components&lt;/summary>
&lt;div class="expand-card-body">&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Cycle &amp;amp; State Segmenter&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Partitions telemetry into meaningful machine phases (conveyor motion, inspection window, sorting actuation), ensuring anomalies are contextual rather than global.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Mode-Aware Normality Model&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Separates “expected variation” (different bottle types, throughput levels, lighting changes) from true abnormality.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Anomaly Scoring + Alarm Logic&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Combines raw anomaly scores with persistence, cooldown, and confidence gates to avoid alert storms.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>RUL / Degradation Module&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Builds interpretable health indicators, estimates trends, and outputs RUL with uncertainty intervals.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Explainability &amp;amp; Evidence Pack Builder&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Produces “what changed” summaries, signal contributions, and local time windows around onset.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Operator Panel + Feedback Loop&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Lets users validate alarms, attach notes, and trigger targeted re-analysis.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/details>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="project-industrialai">
&lt;details class="expand-card">
&lt;summary class="expand-card-title">Evaluation&lt;/summary>
&lt;div class="expand-card-body">&lt;p>The framework is evaluated on the NED bottle inspection and sorting demonstrator under controlled and naturally occurring variability.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Disruption / anomaly classes include:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Conveyor/drive anomalies&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Speed drift, intermittent stalls, rising vibration signatures, abnormal cycle-time variance.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Inspection degradation&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Sensor noise increase, lighting drift, mis-detection patterns, inspection latency spikes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Sorting/actuation issues&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Delay or misfire behaviours, increasing rejection errors, timing misalignment with conveyor state.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Process/context shifts&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Recipe changes, throughput changes, environmental shifts, which must not be misclassified as faults.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Metrics and evidence focus on:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Detection lead time before failure or intervention&lt;/li>
&lt;li>False alarm rate, missed detection rate, and alert stability&lt;/li>
&lt;li>RUL calibration (interval coverage, not only point error)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Robustness across operating modes/recipes&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Operator agreement and triage effectiveness&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Audit completeness (can we reconstruct why an alert fired)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/details>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="project-industrialai">
&lt;details class="expand-card">
&lt;summary class="expand-card-title">Key Findings&lt;/summary>
&lt;div class="expand-card-body">&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Earlier fault visibility&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Mode-aware baselines reduce nuisance alarms while preserving sensitivity to true degradation.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Operationally usable RUL&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Uncertainty-bounded outputs support planning decisions rather than overconfident predictions.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Trust via auditability&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Evidence packs and operator validation pathways make alarms defensible and easier to adopt.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Demonstrator-first realism&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Demonstrator evaluation exposes deployment issues (context shifts, phase alignment, alert storms) that static datasets often hide.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/details>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Human-Centric Spatial Augmented Reality for Interactive (Dis)assembly Operator Assistance</title><link>https://hci2.uk/research/sar/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hci2.uk/research/sar/</guid><description>&lt;p>This project develops a human-centric Spatial Augmented Reality (SAR) system that projects adaptive, light-guided (dis)assembly instructions directly onto the workspace and is controlled through AI-based hand gesture recognition. The system delivers real-time guidance and error feedback without requiring handheld or wearable devices. Beyond guidance, the framework is designed as an intelligent operator assistance system that augments physical and cognitive capabilities, informing users about posture-related physical risk and cognitive state (e.g., workload) while protecting operator identity via privacy-by-design sensing and data handling. User studies show significant reductions in task time, error rates, and perceived workload compared to conventional instruction methods.&lt;/p>
&lt;details class="expand-card">
&lt;summary class="expand-card-title">Motivation&lt;/summary>
&lt;div class="expand-card-body">This project addresses limitations of conventional assembly instructions that rely
on static manuals or wearable devices. By projecting guidance directly onto the
workspace, SAR reduces cognitive load and improves task flow. The project further
targets Industry 5.0 operator assistance by extending SAR from guidance-only to
capability augmentation, combining task awareness with posture and cognitive-state
feedback under privacy-preserving constraints suitable for real shop-floor deployment.&lt;/div>
&lt;/details>
&lt;details class="expand-card">
&lt;summary class="expand-card-title">System Architecture&lt;/summary>
&lt;div class="expand-card-body">The system integrates computer vision, gesture recognition, and spatial projection
to deliver adaptive (dis)assembly instructions in real time. A closed-loop operator
assistance layer estimates task progress and deviations, then adapts projected
cues and feedback. Optional operator-state modules provide posture-aware physical
support and cognitive workload cues, enabling adaptive assistance without exposing
operator identity.&lt;/div>
&lt;/details>
&lt;details class="expand-card">
&lt;summary class="expand-card-title">Key Components&lt;/summary>
&lt;div class="expand-card-body">&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Vision-based workspace perception (parts/steps/progress verification)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Gesture-controlled SAR interface for touchless step navigation and confirmations&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Projection mapping and calibration for spatially registered overlays&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Error detection and feedback cues (missed step, wrong part/order, misalignment)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Operator assistance modules (posture/physical risk cues, cognitive workload inference)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Privacy-by-design pipeline (identity suppression, minimal logging, policy-based retention)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/details>
&lt;details class="expand-card">
&lt;summary class="expand-card-title">Evaluation&lt;/summary>
&lt;div class="expand-card-body">User studies compared SAR guidance with conventional instructions.
Participants showed reduced completion time and fewer errors. Evaluation also
considers cognitive ergonomics and operator acceptance, and, where enabled,
assesses the feasibility of posture- and workload-aware assistance under
privacy-preserving sensing constraints.&lt;/div>
&lt;/details>
&lt;details class="expand-card">
&lt;summary class="expand-card-title">Key Findings&lt;/summary>
&lt;div class="expand-card-body">&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Faster task completion&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Lower error rate&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Reduced perceived workload&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Improved interaction flow via touchless gesture control&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Practical pathway to privacy-preserving operator assistance (capability augmentation)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/details></description></item></channel></rss>