<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Ongoing Research Projects | HCI² Research Lab</title><link>https://hci2.uk/research/</link><atom:link href="https://hci2.uk/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Ongoing Research Projects</description><generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><image><url>https://hci2.uk/media/logo_hu15880263399225826474.png</url><title>Ongoing Research Projects</title><link>https://hci2.uk/research/</link></image><item><title>Human-in-the-Loop Digital Twin for Resilient AMR Fleet Management</title><link>https://hci2.uk/research/digitaltwin/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hci2.uk/research/digitaltwin/</guid><description>&lt;p>This project develops a multi-fidelity, policy-oriented Digital Twin (DT) for resilient Autonomous Mobile Robot (AMR) fleet management under disruption. The system monitors shop-floor telemetry via OPC-UA, classifies incidents (e.g., AMR breakdown, machine unavailability, demand shock), snapshots decision-relevant state, then generates incident-aware recovery schedules under a strict decision-time cap. A surrogate (low-fidelity) optimisation layer produces deployable responses within seconds, while a high-fidelity DT simulation layer provides audit, assurance, and post-decision validation. An operator-in-the-loop panel exposes Pareto trade-offs and schedule previews, enabling transparent selection, re-simulation on demand, and policy-bound overrides, with provenance captured as machine-readable decision artefacts.&lt;/p>
&lt;details class="expand-card">
&lt;summary class="expand-card-title">Motivation&lt;/summary>
&lt;div class="expand-card-body">As AMR fleets scale, small disruptions propagate into congestion, energy waste, and missed throughput targets. Rule-based fleet managers are fast but brittle and opaque during incidents, while high-fidelity simulation is informative but too slow for time-critical response. This project addresses the gap with a governed multi-fidelity DT, fast enough for real-time recovery, and structured enough for auditability, human oversight, and Industry 5.0–ready deployment.&lt;/div>
&lt;/details>
&lt;div class="project-digitaltwin">
&lt;details class="expand-card">
&lt;summary class="expand-card-title">System Architecture&lt;/summary>
&lt;div class="expand-card-body">&lt;h3 id="physical--communication-layer">&lt;strong>Physical &amp;amp; Communication Layer&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>AMRs, stations, sensors, and execution systems stream telemetry and events via &lt;strong>OPC-UA&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Event-driven incident triggers (e.g., fault flags, demand-change flags) initiate response&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="data--digital-shadow-layer">&lt;strong>Data &amp;amp; Digital Shadow Layer&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Telemetry is contextualised and stored (time-series + event envelopes)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>On incident, the system snapshots decision-relevant state, remaining jobs, resource availability, and constraints&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="digital-layer-multi-fidelity-decision-support">&lt;strong>Digital Layer, Multi-Fidelity Decision Support&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Surrogate optimisation (low-fidelity)&lt;/strong>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Generates recovery schedules under a strict decision-time budget&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Targets throughput (makespan) and energy-related objectives&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>High-fidelity DT simulation&lt;/strong>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Executes candidate schedules to validate behavioural realism (e.g., interactions, congestion effects)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Used for audit, assurance, and scenario analysis&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="humanmachine-interaction-layer-operator-panel">&lt;strong>Human–Machine Interaction Layer (Operator Panel)&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Live incident status and fleet state&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Pareto front exploration (trade-off selection)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Gantt schedule previews and validation&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Re-simulation requests and policy-bound overrides with rationale&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="governance--provenance-layer">&lt;strong>Governance &amp;amp; Provenance Layer&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Every incident and decision step is logged with timestamps, reason codes, response type, and operator actions&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Artefacts support traceability, cross-shift handover, and post hoc analysis&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/details>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="project-digitaltwin">
&lt;details class="expand-card">
&lt;summary class="expand-card-title">Key Components&lt;/summary>
&lt;div class="expand-card-body">&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Incident Response Module (IRM)&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Detects incidents from OPC-UA alerts, classifies event type, snapshots state, and triggers recovery.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Response Selector &amp;amp; Model Allocation&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Chooses surrogate-only response vs surrogate + audit vs high-fidelity escalation depending on incident severity, policy, and confidence.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Surrogate-Based Optimisation&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Multi-objective rescheduling under time constraints, balancing throughput and energy-related KPIs while enforcing feasibility and safety constraints.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>High-Fidelity DT Audit&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Validates surrogate decisions, quantifies surrogate–simulation agreement, and provides assurance evidence under disruption.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Operator Panel (Human-in-the-Loop)&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Supports trade-off selection (Pareto), schedule inspection (Gantt), re-simulation, and controlled overrides.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Decision Artefacts &amp;amp; Incident Log&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Structured outputs (status JSON, Pareto results, schedule images, metrics, incident log) enabling governance and reproducibility.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/details>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="project-digitaltwin">
&lt;details class="expand-card">
&lt;summary class="expand-card-title">Evaluation&lt;/summary>
&lt;div class="expand-card-body">&lt;p>The framework is instantiated in an intralogistics use case representing a &lt;strong>battery module assembly flowshop&lt;/strong>, where AMRs transport materials between stations. Evaluation introduces controlled disruption classes to stress-test response performance:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>AMR Breakdown (AMRBD)&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Transport capacity loss, task reassignment, utilisation shift.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Machine Breakdown (MBD)&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Reduced station availability, increased queueing pressure, precedence constraints.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Demand Change (DC)&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
High-priority job injection, schedule reordering, system-wide stress.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Metrics and evidence&lt;/strong> focus on:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Decision latency (stage-resolved, including detection, optimisation, audit/re-simulation, dispatch)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Makespan and energy deviation relative to nominal and baseline dispatch rules&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Schedule stability (reassignments and disturbance propagation)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Surrogate–simulation agreement (validity under high-fidelity execution)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Governance behaviour (policy modes, fidelity escalation, operator intervention pathways)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/details>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="project-digitaltwin">
&lt;details class="expand-card">
&lt;summary class="expand-card-title">Key Findings&lt;/summary>
&lt;div class="expand-card-body">&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Seconds-level incident recovery&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Surrogate optimisation delivers time-bounded rescheduling appropriate for operational incident response.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Multi-fidelity assurance&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
High-fidelity DT execution provides an auditable validation layer, enabling confidence-aware escalation rather than blanket simulation.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Human-in-the-loop governance&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Operator panel interactions (trade-off selection, validation requests, overrides) support accountable decision-making without sacrificing responsiveness.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Transferable blueprint&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
A policy-oriented architecture for AMR fleet management that generalises to other disruption-prone discrete manufacturing intralogistics settings.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/details>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Vision-Enabled SAR for Manual Assembly</title><link>https://hci2.uk/research/sar/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hci2.uk/research/sar/</guid><description>&lt;p>This project develops a human-centric Spatial Augmented Reality (SAR) system that projects adaptive, light-guided assembly instructions directly onto the workspace and is controlled through AI-based hand gesture recognition. The system delivers real-time guidance and error feedback without requiring handheld or wearable devices. Beyond guidance, the framework is designed as an intelligent operator assistance system that augments physical and cognitive capabilities, informing users about posture-related physical risk and cognitive state (e.g., workload) while protecting operator identity via privacy-by-design sensing and data handling. User studies show significant reductions in task time, error rates, and perceived workload compared to conventional instruction methods.&lt;/p>
&lt;details class="expand-card">
&lt;summary class="expand-card-title">Motivation&lt;/summary>
&lt;div class="expand-card-body">This project addresses limitations of conventional assembly instructions that rely
on static manuals or wearable devices. By projecting guidance directly onto the
workspace, SAR reduces cognitive load and improves task flow. The project further
targets Industry 5.0 operator assistance by extending SAR from guidance-only to
capability augmentation, combining task awareness with posture and cognitive-state
feedback under privacy-preserving constraints suitable for real shop-floor deployment.&lt;/div>
&lt;/details>
&lt;details class="expand-card">
&lt;summary class="expand-card-title">System Architecture&lt;/summary>
&lt;div class="expand-card-body">The system integrates computer vision, gesture recognition, and spatial projection
to deliver adaptive assembly instructions in real time. A closed-loop operator
assistance layer estimates task progress and deviations, then adapts projected
cues and feedback. Optional operator-state modules provide posture-aware physical
support and cognitive workload cues, enabling adaptive assistance without exposing
operator identity.&lt;/div>
&lt;/details>
&lt;details class="expand-card">
&lt;summary class="expand-card-title">Key Components&lt;/summary>
&lt;div class="expand-card-body">&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Vision-based workspace perception (parts/steps/progress verification)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Gesture-controlled SAR interface for touchless step navigation and confirmations&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Projection mapping and calibration for spatially registered overlays&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Error detection and feedback cues (missed step, wrong part/order, misalignment)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Operator assistance modules (posture/physical risk cues, cognitive workload inference)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Privacy-by-design pipeline (identity suppression, minimal logging, policy-based retention)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/details>
&lt;details class="expand-card">
&lt;summary class="expand-card-title">Evaluation&lt;/summary>
&lt;div class="expand-card-body">User studies compared SAR guidance with conventional instructions.
Participants showed reduced completion time and fewer errors. Evaluation also
considers cognitive ergonomics and operator acceptance, and, where enabled,
assesses the feasibility of posture- and workload-aware assistance under
privacy-preserving sensing constraints.&lt;/div>
&lt;/details>
&lt;details class="expand-card">
&lt;summary class="expand-card-title">Key Findings&lt;/summary>
&lt;div class="expand-card-body">&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Faster task completion&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Lower error rate&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Reduced perceived workload&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Improved interaction flow via touchless gesture control&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Practical pathway to privacy-preserving operator assistance (capability augmentation)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/details></description></item></channel></rss>